גוט וואך. Gut vokh. Today's דף daf is נ"ו, nun vav, which
is the big beginning of a major אגדתא aggadata on the destruction
of the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, but we first pick up at
the bottom of נ"ה עמוד ב' nun hey amud bais in the
גמרא Gemara on the משנה. mishnah. And the משנה mishnah seemingly because
we were dealing with certain תקנות takkanos and relating to things that
are stolen and so on, that was property that was seized by
a סיקריקון, sicricon, a type of assassin, and at what stage would
we say that if a third party, somebody else purchased it from
him, he he owns it or does not own it. So let's
take a look. And that was in the context of before or
after the wars of חורבן הבית. Churban HaBayis. So the גמרא Gemara
says like this: השתא בהרוגי מלחמה לא היה סיקריקון מהרוגי מלחמה ואילך
יש סיקריקון? Hashta b'harugei milchama lo haya sicricon, me'harugei milchama v'ilech yesh
sicricon? The משנה mishnah says that this סיקריקון sicricon didn't exist at
the time of the those the wars of the חורבן הבית, Churban
HaBayis, literally those that were murdered during the war. How much more
so, if it was at that, if there weren't that, that phenomenon
didn't exist then, did it exist after that? So אמר רב יהודה,
Amar Rav Yehuda, no, לא דנו בדין סיקריקון קאמר. lo dunu b'din
sicricon ka'amar. No, no, no, it means that at that time the
obviously the phenomenon of the was there of the סיקריקון, sicricon, but
the law that the משנה mishnah is talking about did not apply.
דאמר רב אסי, D'amar Rav Assi, ג' גזירות גזרו. Gimmel gezeiros gazru.
There were three edicts at the time of the חורבן הבית. Churban
HaBayis. גזירה קמייתא, Gezeira Kamaisa, the first edict, כל דלא קטיל ליקטלוהו.
Kol d'lo katil liktlu'u. Any presumably like Roman soldier that does not
kill a Jew will be killed. מציעתא, Metzi'asa, the middle edict was
כל דקטיל ליתי ארבע זוזי. Kol d'katil leisi arba zuzei. So it
wasn't that you were you would get killed if you didn't kill
a Jew, but if you did kill a Jew, you would be
rewarded with four
זוז. zuz. ובתרייתא, U'basraisa, the final גזירה gezeira was כל דקטיל ליקטלוהו.
Kol d'katil liktlu'u. They were trying to instill after I guess the
time of the war itself, maybe there was during the war they
were trying to murder kill all the Jews, after the war they
were maybe trying to do some mop-up operation, and then but finally
then when they were after the transition period they were trying to
reinstill order, and then they said at this stage anybody that were
to kill would kill a Jew would be killed. הילכך Hilkach קמייתא
מציעתא, Kamaisa Metzi'asa, the first and second stages where you were obligated
or at least rewarded to kill a Jew, so כיון דקטלי, keivan
d'katlei, since he would be killed, אגב אונסיה גמור ומקני.
agav onseh gamur makni. If you were basically told by a Roman
soldier, by one of these guys, give me your land and I
won't kill you, you knew that he really was going to kill
you because he would at least get rewarded for that. So you
really wanted him to just take the land and you had real
full intent to give him the land to save your life. So
in that case anybody who would buy the land after from him
would own it. You wouldn't have to come back and even buy
it from you. You had totally you had totally given it to
that Roman. But בתרייתא, basraisa, by the third edict where the person
was not allowed to kill you, אמר, amar, so he's threatening your
life, but he's not allowed to kill you. So when you give
him the land, you don't really want to sell him the land
because you say to yourself, האידנא לישקול, Idna lishkol, let him take
it today, ולמחר תבענא ליה בדינא, u'lemachar tavna lei b'dina, and then
tomorrow I'll be able to pursue him in court. Okay? So in
the third case, even though you gave him the land, you didn't
really want to give it to him, you just gave it to
him because temporarily you couldn't, but you knew that you hoped you
expected that you would have some type of legal recourse. And in
that case, if somebody were to buy the land off the סיקריקון
sicricon after he took it from you, he would still have to
go back and buy it from you, and buy it from you
in the right order to know that you really wanted to sell
it to him.
Okay. So the גמרא Gemara is now not analyzing the specifics in
the משנה, mishnah, it just sort of laid that as a almost
as a backdrop to now transition into the אגדתא aggadata about חורבן
הבית, Churban HaBayis, because now it laid this period of חורבן הבית
Churban HaBayis where they were killing all the Jews. But it's interesting,
it didn't sort of unpack the משנה, mishnah, but the idea of
the משנה mishnah is, is that now the non-Jew, the סיקריקון sicricon
doesn't really own it, so you a third party are going to
buy it from the סיקריקון, sicricon, if you first buy it from
the סיקריקון sicricon and then from the original owner, it's not a
good purchase because he's doing it out of fear because he wants
the סיקריקון sicricon he knows that the סיקריקון sicricon wants the sale
to go through. And the only way it works is if you
first buy it from the owner and then from the סיקריקון. sicricon.
That was stage one and then stage two was presumably it was
a sense that was not likely that the original owner
was going to get it back, so you basically it led to
a position where either the original owner had the right to the
first right to purchase it from the סיקריקון, sicricon, and if he
didn't, you bought it from the סיקריקון sicricon and gave the owner
a quarter of the value. So that was stage two of the
תקנה. takkanah. Again the גמרא Gemara is not really going into that,
it's transitioning straight into the אגדתא aggadata now of חורבן הבית. Churban
HaBayis. Yes, Charlie.
Does this little סוגיא suggya have any impact on the מחלוקת machlokes
over whether non-Jews can own land in ארץ ישראל? Eretz Yisrael?
Well, yeah, there's not a question about whether they can, well, yes,
the reality was obviously they would purchase land and own land. The
question is whether that would have a status regarding תרומות ומעשרות, Terumos
u'Maasros, how much legally according to הלכה halacha would they... have a
right to change the actual structure of land but the reality was
we weren't always in control of that situation and the reality was
was that they would own land. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara
says, now it's going to transition into חורבן הבית, Churban ha-Bayis, without
interestingly, like I said, with sort of like just glossing over the
legal aspects of this, the הלכה halachic aspects of the משנה. Mishna.
אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabi Yochanan, said רבי יוחנן, Rabi Yochanan, מאי
דכתיב, mai d'chsiv, what's meant by the verse? אשרי אדם מפחד תמיד,
ashrei adam m'fached tamid, praised is the person that is constantly afraid.
What does that mean?
So ומקשה לבו יפול ברעה, u-maksheh libo yipol b'ra-ah, and one who
strengthens his heart will fall into evil. אקמצא ובר קמצא חרוב ירושלים.
a-Kamtza u-var Kamtza charuv Yerushalayim. So ירושלים Yerushalayim was destroyed because of
the story of קמצא Kamtza and בר קמצא. Bar Kamtza.
אתרנגולא ותרנגולתא חרוב טור מלכא. a-tarnagola v'tarnagolta charuv Tur Malka. The, the
טור מלכא, Tur Malka, this city was destroyed because of a chicken
and a rooster, because of a hen and a rooster,
rooster and a hen. אשקא דריספק, a-shaka d'rispak, and for like some
type of a, of an axle of a, or a wall of
a carriage,
חרוב ביתר, charuv Beitar, ביתר Beitar was destroyed. And now we're going
to look and see what does it have to do with the
פסוק pasuk that we quoted? So the most obvious is going to
be the issue about מקשה לבו, maksheh libo, you know, strengthen your
heart. I mean, obviously people know the story of קמצא Kamtza and
בר קמצא Bar Kamtza about the person that did not have any
sympathy for this guy that was accidentally invited into his house and
so on. So it has to do with like a hardness of
heart. But also the, the beginning of the פסוק pasuk of אשרי
אדם מפחד תמיד, ashrei adam m'fached tamid, which tells, which is, you
know, that is basically, doesn't just mean like somebody who's constantly anxious,
but somebody who is, you know, fearful of, you know, concerned about
their actions and concerned that they're doing the right thing and so
on. Like one explanation is you're afraid for your, about your sins.
You know, so it's a right type of a concern about, about,
so therefore and these are people that showed no concern that, you
know, their actions or no concern for the impending possible destruction of
ירושלים, Yerushalayim, and were just constantly, you know, very much like,
you know, sort of like approaching things with like blinders on. So
that's like the reverse of the, of the מקשה לבו. maksheh libo.
Okay, so these are people that don't have any concern about the
bigger picture, about what might be happening, and we'll see that in
the story. And are, you know, very focused on just the here
and now and not thinking about the possible ramifications and also this
hardness of heart. So let's take a look.
אקמצא
ובר קמצא. a-Kamtza u-var Kamtza. אקמצא ובר קמצא חרוב ירושלים. a-Kamtza u-var
Kamtza charuv Yerushalayim. Now it's also worth mentioning that like קמצא Kamtza
means like, you know, is like somebody, like to like grab, to
like hold back, you know, it's like it's like stinginess, it's, you
know, what's the right word?
Anyway, like anyway, but somebody, it's the opposite of generosity. Miserly. What?
Miserliness, right, to be like, you know, a קומץ kometz is a
handbreadth like you close everything in your hand, right. So a lack
of generosity of spirit is also the, you know, obviously those words
are significant. חרוב ירושלים. Charuv Yerushalayim. דההוא גברא דרחמיה קמצא. D'hahu gavra
d'rachmei Kamtza. There
was a man who his, his, his good friend was קמצא. Kamtza.
ובעל דבביה בר קמצא. u-va-al devaveih Bar Kamtza. And his enemy was
בר קמצא. Bar Kamtza. עבד סעודתא. Avad se-udasa.
And he made a feast, this person. אמר ליה לשמעיה. Amar leih
l'shameih. He said to his attendant, זיל אייתי לי קמצא. zil aysei
li Kamtza. Go and invite for me קמצא, Kamtza, my friend. אזל
אייתי ליה בר קמצא. Azal aysei leih Bar Kamtza. He went and
he accidentally invited בר קמצא. Bar Kamtza. אתא אשכחיה דהוה יתיב. Asa
ashchecheih d'hava yasiv.
So the host found בר קמצא Bar Kamtza that was sitting. אמר
ליה מכדי ההוא גברא בעל דבבא דההוא גברא הוא. Amar leih michdi
hahu gavra ba-al devava d'hahu gavra hu. So this is, this guy's
my enemy. מאי בעית הכא? mai ba-yis hacha? What's he doing here?
קום פוק, Kum puk, get out of here. אמר ליה, Amar leih,
so בר קמצא Bar Kamtza says to the host, הואיל ואתאי שבקן,
ho-il v'asai shavkan, since I'm already here, just leave me alone, let
me stay, don't embarrass me. ויהיבנא לך דמי מאי דאכילנא, v'yahivna lach
dmei mai d'achilna, I'll pay you for what I'm eating. ושתיינא, u-shasyana,
and I'm drinking. אמר ליה, Amar leih, he said to him, לא,
lo, I refuse. אמר ליה, Amar leih, יהיבנא לך דמי פלגא דסעודתך.
yahivna lach dmei palga d'se-udatach.
I'll give you half of the cost of my feast. אמר ליה
לא, Amar leih lo, no. אמר ליה יהיבנא לך דמי כולא סעודתך.
Amar leih yahivna lach dmei kula se-udatach. I'm not, not of my
field, of the whole, of the whole feast, I'll pay you for
the whole feast. אמר ליה לא, Amar leih lo, no. נקטיה בידיה.
Naktye b'yadeih. He was so committed to his enmity and you know
to his hatred, right, and so he took him in his hand.
ואוקמיה ואפקיה. v'okmeih v'afkeih. He stood him up and he, and he
like cast him out. אמר. Amar. הואיל. Ho-il.
One also wonders if there's a little bit of a like also
of a metaphor here, you know, about the siege of ירושלים, Yerushalayim,
right. You know, that like people that are so committed to being,
you know, to being at war they're not able, you know, to
kicking people out, right, so obviously on the one hand it's the
Romans, but it's also, you know, as we're going to see, it's
the, it's the zealots within the city. Right, so people that are
just so committed to their enmity and their hatred and so on
that they're not able to switch gears, you know, even when there's
a much obvious other course that could be, you know, could make
things much better.
Yeah, בר קמצא Bar Kamtza probably thought that this guy's name was
never named was trying to...
Right, appease him or something... Right, exactly, exactly.
Okay. So נקטיה בידיה ואוקמיה ואפקיה Naktei beyadei ve-okmei ve-afkei
and he took, kicked him out. אמר הואיל והוו יתבי רבנן ולא
מחו ביה, Amar ho'il vehavu yatvi rabbanan velo machu bei,
since there was rabbis at that meal and they did not stop
him, they did not protest, שמע מינא כניחא להו, shema mina kanicha
lehu, we see that they're okay with it, which also raises another
theme about, you know, about what's the statement? The only thing evil
men need to flourish is for, you know, good men to stand
by and do nothing, right? So the other theme about the people
that were not directly active in bringing these, the destruction about, but
they act but through their inaction and through the fact that they
did not stand up and protest. Okay.
Maybe they didn't see in this case, but anyway that doesn't matter.
I mean he thought they did. But again I think that the
larger theme here is also pointing to the responsibility that the rabbis
had. You know, it's very nice to blame the Zealots and to
blame this and whatever. Who are the people that weren't in a
position either even before things got to a crisis moment that they
could have redirected certain courses of events or when things got to
the crisis moment? Right, and we're going to see that about the
ways in which the rabbis let things happen, right? So that's another
major theme here is about the people who are to blame not
because of what they did but because of what they could have
done and didn't do.
שמע מינא כניחא להו, Shema mina kanicha lehu, so we see they're
okay with it. איזיל איכול בהו קורצא בי מלכא. Izil eichol behu
kurtza bei malka. Let me go and sort of, this phrase of,
'to eat' בהו קורצא behu kurtza is an idiomatic phrase but it
means basically, let me go and like and spread, you know, evil
report about them, מלשין malshin on them, libel them in the house
of the King, of the Caesar. אזל אמר ליה לקיסר. Azal amar
lei le-keisar. He went and he said to the Caesar, מרדו בך
יהודאי. Mardu becha yehudai. The Jews are rebelling. אמר ליה מי יימר.
Amar lei mi yeimar. Says who? אמר ליה שדר להו קורבנא. Amar
lei shadar lehu korbana. Go send them a sacrifice. חזי אי מקרבין
ליה, Chazi i makrivin lei, and you'll see if they'll offer it
up. אזל שדר בידיה עגלא תילתא. Azal shadar beyadei egla tilta. He
went and he sent to him a this third calf, whether that
does that mean there's a whole debate about exactly what that means,
but anyway Tosafot just says it means a very fattened calf. ובהדי
דקאתי, Ve-haday de-ka-atei, as Bar Kamtza was bringing it to ירושלים, Yerushalayim,
שדי ביה מומא, shadi bei muma, he made a blemish in it.
בניב שפתים, Be-niv sefatayim, in like its upper lip.
Also ניב שפתים, niv sefatayim, you know, indication about speech and the
power of speech in all of these stories, which we will see.
ואמרי לה בדוקין שבעין, Ve-amri lah be-dukin she-ba-ayin, and some say it's
in a tiny little like a cataract of the eye.
So דוכתא דלדידן הוי מומא, Duchta de-ledidan havei muma, something that for
us is a it's a tiny little blemish but for us it
counts as a blemish. ולדידהו לאו מומא הוא. U-ledidehu lav muma hu.
But where for their sacrifices they don't consider that a blemish, so
the Romans wouldn't realize that there's a problem with this animal, but
the Jews wouldn't be able to offer it up. סבור רבנן לקרוביה
משום שלום מלכות. Savar rabbanan le-kruvei mishum shelom malchut. So the rabbis
at the time, again it's interesting that it's the rabbis since it
was probably the כהנים kohanim and the Sadducees that had more control
over what was going on in the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. But
be that as it may, the rabbis at the time thought to
offer it up משום שלום מלכות. mishum shelom malchut.
Just adopting that attitude though, which is also important. That attitude that
yeah we should we should bend the rules.
Exactly, so exactly. So here you actually see an approach of like
oh you mean that you know as opposed to like the Sadducees
or more more flexible you mean in
general right whoever it was the Gemara's adopting that
right exactly that they should have bent the rules and they would
be the wiser for it.
Exactly and that gets exactly to right exactly as opposed to that
we were seeing that we're sort of already like you know telegraphing
the idea of like rabbis standing by and not acting and being
very stuck in your ways and not being able to be flexible.
And here the rabbis have an opportunity to do something to actually
bend the rules, be flexible, see the bigger picture, and do it
because of you know to because you got the Roman government there
you want to make peace with them. אמר להו רבי זכריה בן
אבקולס. Amar lehu Rabbi Zecharia ben Avkulos. So
this Rabbi Zecharia ben Avkulos who I don't know if we ever
hear about him any other time said, יאמרו בעלי מומין קריבין לגבי
מזבח. Yomeru ba'alei mumin kreivin legabi mizbeach. What? You can't do that!
People are gonna think that you can bring a בעל מום ba'al
mum to the altar. Okay, so therefore because of that you know
of that sort of very classic way of looking at things it
can you know very sort of you know about these these small
little concerns not being able to see the bigger picture and not
being able to bend the rules. סבור למיקטליה. Savar le-miktalei. So they
said fine, if we can't go ahead if we can't bring this
because of halachic concerns, let's kill this Bar Kamtza guy. דלא ליזיל
ולימא, De-lo leizil ve-leima, so he shouldn't go and report back to
us to the Roman government. אמר להו רבי זכריה. Amar lehu Rabbi
Zecharia. So Rabbi Zecharia said, יאמרו מטיל מום בקדשים יהרג. Yomeru matil
mum be-kodashim yehareg. People will say that the punishment for blemishings a
sacrifice is that you're put to death. So you know such this
concern about the halachic implications that other people will learn from it
and not this obviously much bigger concern about the Roman government.
אמר רבי יוחנן. Amar Rabbi Yochanan. So Rabbi Yochanan said, ענוותנותו של
רבי זכריה בן אבקולס החריבה את ביתנו ושרפה
את היכלנו והגליתנו מארצנו. Anvetanuto shel Rabbi Zecharia ben Avkulos hechriva et
beiteinu ve-sarfa et heichaleinu ve-higlitnu me-artzeinu. So
the humility of Rabbi Zecharia ben Avkulas destroyed our house and burnt
the and burnt the היכל, Heichal, you know, destroyed the בית המקדש,
Beis HaMikdash, burnt the היכל, Heichal, the sanctuary, and caused us to
exile from our land. Now it's pretty interesting because first of all,
why to describe it as humility? But what it means is that
sometimes, you know, you need to take a little bit of initiative,
that you can't just say like oh who are we to change
הלכה, Halacha, who are we to do something out of bounds, right?
So as opposed to sort of seeing this, I mean you could
have said his like his obstinacy, right, his, you know, you know,
his aggressiveness, he wouldn't let us change things, but it could also
be framed as like, you know, no, who are we to change
things like you know and like so so it so it sort
of puts the other side in this sort of, you know, on
the defensive. Like we're trying to you're who you know who who
do you think we are that we can go ahead and change
the הלכה Halacha whatever? So you know it it it it's a
way in which this position which is not the wise course of
action here, but it's framed as the very פרום frum one, as
the humble one, as the one, you know, of who are we
to make those types of changes. So number one. But the other
interesting thing you need to that needs to be pointed out is
that it's very nice that they're pointing the finger at him, but
obviously the rabbis weren't willing to take him on, you know, so
was I mean he might have been the part of the reason,
right, but how about the other part about the rabbis who stood
back and weren't willing to take him on and to say no,
you know, we gotta look at the bigger picture here. Yes, Charlie.
Could בר קמצא Bar Kamtza have had the דין din of a
מוסר? moser?
Yeah, he could have obviously, he would have, but that's but the
point here is that this רבי זכריה Rabbi Zechariah was afraid that
people would misinterpret it.
And there are a lot of great sages who around at that
time and who is this...
Right, exactly. So it's very nice that they say his humility, but
you know, but some but the rabbis have to take responsibility for
not standing up to him too. Their humility also that they didn't
stand up to him.
This is sort of a cast a light perhaps the idea that
where you find God's greatness you find His ענווה. anavah. Right? So
what is the the greatness can be this ענווה, anavah, the or
you
know it could be sometimes called for
to be like רבי זכריה. Rabbi Zechariah.
Right, right, exactly. Yeah.
Do you see any connection with the previous what we studied yesterday
about the thief's and those being
accepted and they
actually made a change on that level?
Right, I mean that's an excellent point, you know, which is so
that's a really the next point which didn't occur to me but
so much of the entire פרק perek and a half and you're
talking about just yesterday was about the rabbis exercising their power for
the sake of תיקון עולם tikkun olam and making radical change, like
a woman, you know, who should be who shouldn't be divorced made
her divorced because of הפקר בית דין הפקר, hefker beis din hefker,
something that shouldn't be a קרבן korban making it into a קרבן,
korban, like real power on like profound like not just, you know,
monetary issues, but you know, issues about the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash
and קרבנות korbanos and personal status and all these things, which is
like a real expression of rabbinic power, right? And it's like for
you know, so that's a really excellent point, you know, that contrast.
In a way maybe that's like the תיקון, tikkun, like you know,
we realize after we completely sort of, you know, sort of you
know, renounced our responsibility, you know, in the in the course of
events here that we really have to own that power and own
that responsibility. So that's a really excellent point that's not occurred to
me to see the whole previous thing as like as you know
these things in contrast. Like look what happens if you have too
much ענווה. anavah. Who are we to change the law? Who are
we to do anything? Right, disaster happens, right? That's an excellent point.
Yeah.
Okay.
Okay. שדר עלויה לנירון קיסר. Shadar alaihu le'Neron Keisar. So they so
they sent against them, you know, Neron, Nero, Caesar. So
so Nero was now coming to do war against them. כי קאתא,
Ki ka'asa, as he was drawing close, שדא גירא, Shada gira, he
shot an arrow למזרח, le'mizrach, to the east. אתא נפל בירושלים, Asa
nefal bi'Yerushalayim, it fell towards the direction of Jerusalem. He was doing
this to like, you know, to divine, you know, whether this was
the right course of events.
למערב, Le'ma'arav, to the west. אתא נפל בירושלים, Asa nefal bi'Yerushalayim, it
fell towards Jerusalem. לארבע רוחות השמים, Le'arba ruchos ha'shamayim, to all four
directions. אתא נפל בירושלים. Asa nefal bi'Yerushalayim. So it was clear that
it was like divinely ordained that he should come and destroy Jerusalem.
אמר ליה לינוקא. Amar lei le'yanuka.
Every which direction that you can think of. What? All face Jerusalem?
Oh, because every direction goes to Jerusalem. אמר ליה לינוקא, Amar lei
le'yanuka, so he said to a child, פסוק לי פסוקיך, Pesok li
pesukecha, tell me the פסוק pasuk that you're reading. Of course this
is obviously this is a way the rabbis would sort of try
to, you know, divine God's will and now they're putting this in
the mouth of Nero. But anyway, tell me what what biblical verse
you happen to be reading. אמר ליה, Amar lei, he said to
Nero there, ונתתי את נקמתי באדום, Ve'nasati es nikmasi be'Edom, I will
do my I will give my do my vengeance against אדום, Edom,
which for the rabbis meant Rome. ביד עמי ישראל, Be'yad ami Yisrael,
through My nation Israel. אמר, Amar, so Nero said, קודשא בריך הוא
בעי לחרובי ביתיה, Kudsha Berich Hu ba'ei le'charuvi beiseih, it's clear He
wants His בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash destroyed because all the arrows are
falling towards Jerusalem. ובעי לקיחויי ידיה בהוא גברא u-ba'ei le-kichuyei yadeih be-hu
gavra he's going to wipe his hands on me. So he's going
to get me to do his dirty work because it says he'll
take his vengeance against אדום Edom and then he and then he's
going to get me to do his dirty work and then he's
going to blame it all on me. So I'm not going to
be part of this. Okay so ערק ואזיל arak va-azil he ran
away and he went ואיגייר ve-igaier and he converted. Now why he
converted I don't know I mean you think God here's trying to
blame get me to do his dirty
work but now the Jews are about to have their בית המקדש
Beis HaMikdash destroyed what?
To be on the winning side.
The eventual winning side, the side that's going to be losing for
the here and now. Yeah but okay anyway ונפק מיניה ve-nafik mineih
apparently this is Nero the Caesar this is in the rabbinic imagination
okay. ונפק מיניה ve-nafik mineih רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. Now Rabbi Meir
descended from Nero. I don't know what we're supposed to make from
that that Rabbi Meir and why they picked Nero I guess because
Nero was was Nero the Caesar right before Vespasian was he the
one I mean?
There were three short, I
knew somebody would know it,
between Nero and Vespasian who were great each lasting less than a
year each.
Aha but soon after Nero was
Vespasian was the first significant emperor after Nero.
So okay okay anyway okay שדריה עילויה לאספסיינוס קיסר. shadreih ilaveih le-Aspasyanus
keisar. So they sent now against him
Vespasian alright. Now obviously as we're going to see Vespasian here calls
him Vespasian the Caesar Vespasian but he was not yet the Caesar
in the way this in this story. Okay so he's now this
Vespasian who's now a general is waging war coming to besiege Jerusalem.
אתא צר עלה תלת שני. ata tzar alah telat shani. He besieged
it for three years. הוו בה הנהו תלתא עתירא. havu bah hanahu
telata atira. There were three wealthy people in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. נקדימון בן
גוריון Nakdimon Ben Guryon
who we hear about elsewhere ובן כלבא שבוע. u-Ben Kalba Savua. Ben
Kalba Savua who was רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva's father-in-law.
Right wasn't he Rabbi Akiva's father-in-law Ben Kalba Savua? I think so
in another story.
What?
His wife's father.
His wife's father, his father-in-law. ובן ציצית הכסת u-Ben Tzitzit HaKeset and
somebody called Ben Tzitzit HaKeset. Yeah although right okay Ben Tzitzit HaKeset.
נקדימון בן גוריון Nakdimon Ben Guryon so who's Nakdimon Ben Guryon what
does that name mean? שנקדה לו חמה בעבורו. shenakdah lo chamah ba-avuro.
Somehow he was like so wealthy it was as if the sun
pierced through the heavens for his sake. בן כלבא שבוע Ben Kalba
Savua שכל הנכנס לביתו כשהוא רעב ככלב יוצא כשהוא שבע. she-kol ha-nichnas
le-beiso keshehu ra'ev kekelev yetzei keshehu savei'a. Anybody would go into his
house when he was hungry as hungry as a dog would come
out as sated would come out sated, the sated dog. בן ציצית
הכסת Ben Tzitzit HaKeset שהיתה ציציתו נגררת על גבי כסתות shehayesah tzitziyaso
nigreret al gabei kesasos that his fringes of his garment would be
would drag on pillows people would walk around carrying pillows by him
so that the fringes of his garment wouldn't touch the ground. איכא
דאמרי ika de-amri some say שהיתה כסתו מוטלת בין גדולי רומי shehayesah
kisaso muteset bein gedolei Romi his chair would be would be among
the the great
prestigious people of Rome. Okay anyway חד אמר להו chad amar lehu
one said to them אנא זיינא להו בחיטי ושערי ana zaina lehu
be-chitei u-se'ari I will support all of Jerusalem because they're now besieged
they're not getting any stuff coming in, I'll support all of them
with wheat and
and what's it called with wheat and barley. וחד אמר להו ve-chad
amar lehu and one said to them בדחמרא ובדמלחא be-dechmra u-ve-dimlcha I
will I will take care of providing all of the wine and
salt ומשחא u-mishcha oil. וחד אמר להו ve-chad amar lehu and another
one said to all the people of ירושלים Yerushalayim בדציבי be-detzivi I
will support them with like chips of wood with like firewood. ושבחו
רבנן לדתציבי ve-shabchu rabanan le-detzivi
and the Rabbis praised the one who would support them with the
firewood more than the other two. Why? דרב חסדא de-Rav Chisda כל
אקלידי הוי מסר לשמעיה kol aklidi havei masar le-shameih Rav Chisda would
give over all his keys to his attendant בר מדציבי bar mi-detzivi
except for the keys to the firewood house storage facility. דאמר רב
חסדא de-amar Rav Chisda אקליבא דחיטי בעיא שיתין אקליבי דציבי akliba de-chitei
ba'eia shisin aklibei de-detzivi
one warehouse of wheat requires sixty warehouses of firewood to to bake
the wheat right? It's like they say how much like grazing land
is required to
produce one pound of meat right? So anyway so the guy who's
providing the the firewood was obviously a huge amount I don't know
if his value was obviously firewood presumably is cheaper than wheat and
other things but anyway it was a huge amount.
Under siege storage space is a premium.
That's true, that's a good point.
Okay anyway הוו להו למיזן עשרין וחד שתא havu lehu le-meizan esrin
ve-chad shata they could have supported Jerusalem in siege for twenty-one years.
Obviously this is a bit of an exaggeration. Anyway הוו בהו הנהו
בריוני. havu behu hanahu biryoni. Now there were these בריוני biryoni which
are basically seems to be the Zealots. And I don't know what's
the
what's the etymology of that word? Does he give it there Steinzaltz?
Oh here we are.
The source
of this word has not been found.
There you go,
it says from the root בור bor empty.
Yeah I don't think that's really it.
Anyway the Zealots mostly to Praetorian, Praetoriai.
Praetoriai? Yeah that's from the life of Brian I remember it.
Oh
I see I see.
Anyway it
was it was.
Okay, but no, this seems to be, no, but this seems to
be that they were Jews. It was the, the Zealot guard.
Palace Guards? Really? So it was Romans? But no, from the context
it's clear it was the Zealot. Anyway, אמר להו רבנן, Amar lehu
rabanan, נפק ונעביד שלמא בהדייהו. Nafek vena'avid shelma bahadeihu. So let's go
out, the Rabbis here, for once, right, they were trying to be
the ones to see the bigger picture and they wanted to make
peace. Let's go out and let's make peace, you know, let's just
surrender and make peace. אבל לא שבקינהו, Aval lo shabkinhu, they wouldn't
allow them. אמרו להו, Ameru lehu, נפק ונעביד קרבא בהדייהו. Nafek vena'avid
karva bahadeihu. So now the Zealots said, no, let's go war against
them. אמרו להו רבנן, Ameru lehu rabanan, the Rabbis said, it won't
work out. לא מסתייעא מילתא, Lo mistaye'a milta, it won't work out,
you're not going to, which is a phrase that also means like
God won't help you, you know, but it's not going to work
out, you won't succeed. קמו, Kamu, so in order to force the
people to go to war, what the Zealots did is they got
up, קלינהו להנהו אמברי דחטי ושערי. Kalin'hu lehannu ambarei dechitti usha'arei. They
burned down the warehouses of wheat and barley, okay, to force people
you have no choice so you have to go to war, you
know, you have to fight. והוה כפנא, Vehavah kafna, and there was
a famine.
מרתא בת בייתוס, Marta Bat Baitos, Martha the daughter of Baitos,
עתירתא דירושלים הויא. Atirta deYerushalayim havaia. She was one of the wealthy
people of Yerushalayim. We also know about בייתוס, Baitos, בייתוס בן זונין,
Baitos ben Zonin, he appears in a number of stories. One minute.
שדרתהו לשליחא, Shadratehu lishlicha, there's such a great story, she sent her
שליח shaliach ואמרה ליה, ve'amra lei, and she says to him, זיל
אייתי לי סמידא, Zil aeiti li smida, go get for me fine
flour. אדאזל, Adazal, by the time he got to the market, right,
איזדבין, izdabin, it was all sold. אתא ואמר לה, Ata ve'amar la,
he came back and said to her, סמידא ליכא, Smida leika, there's
no fine flour, חיוורתא איכא, chivarta ika, but there's still the, you
know, white flour. אמרה ליה, Amra lei, fine, זיל אייתי לי, zil
aeiti li, go get it for me. אדאזל איזדבין, Adazal izdabin, by
the time he got back, that had sold. אתא ואמר לה, Ata
ve'amar la, came back and said to her, חיוורתא ליכא, Chivarta leika,
there's no white flour, גושקרא איכא, gushkara ika, there's like more coarse
flour. אמרה
ליה, Amra lei, she said to him, זיל אייתי לי, zil aeiti
li, you would think at one of these stages she would have
just said, just get me whatever is available.
Anyway, if she also had a cell phone she could have like
just texted her. Anyway, go get it for me. אדאזל איזדבין, Adazal
izdabin, by the time he got there that was sold. אתא ואמר
לה, Ata ve'amar la, he said back to her, came back and
said to her, גושקרא ליכא, Gushkara leika, there's no coarse flour, קימחא
דשערי איכא, kimcha desha'arei ika, but there's still barley flour. אמרה ליה,
Amra lei, זיל אייתי לי, zil aeiti li, go get it for
me. אדאזל איזדבין, Adazal izdabin,
okay, it also got sold. הות שלפא מסאנא, Havah shalpa masana, she
was, you know, she took off her shoe, אמרת, amrat, and she
said, איפוק ואחזי, ipok ve'achzei, let me go out and see אי
משכחנא מידי למיכל, ei meshkachna midi lemeichal, if I have found anything
to eat. איתיב לה פרשא בכרעא, Aitiv lah parsha bechar'a, she stuck
her foot into some cow dung, ומתה, umeta, and she died because
she was so, you know, disgusted from it, she had been so
refined and now she was just so, you know, overwhelmed by like
this disgust of it, ומתה. umeta. קרי עליה רבן יוחנן בן זכאי,
Kari aleih Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai, Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai read about
her the verse, one minute, הרכה בך והענוגה אשר לא נסתה כף
רגלה, Haraka becha vehanuga asher lo nista chaf ragla,
the delicate one that her foot has not ever been put on
the ground, you know, מתענגת מרוב, mit'anegat merov, so you know
from her delicacy, so here this curse was coming to her. I
don't know why she took off her shoes though. Anyway, yes, why
didn't she put on her shoes when she was going out?
Yes, she was יהושע בן גמלא's Yehoshua ben Gamla wife.
Okay, so she and all that money she used to buy the
high priesthood for him.
Oh, that's an interesting point. Right, right, right, I'd forgotten that, that
she was the one that bought the high priesthood. Right. Okay,
does that say anything about why it says she took off her
shoe?
No, I don't think she took off her shoe deliberately.
It says she wasn't wearing shoes. הות משלפא מסאנא, Havah meshalfa masana,
she was barefoot, yeah, but she didn't put her on as to...
right, she didn't bother to put them on when she went out.
But okay, okay, fine. Where are we? That's true, what it means
her shoes were off. Okay, where were we? איכא
דאמרי, Ika de'amrei,
some say גרוגרות דרבי צדוק אכלה, grogerot deRabbi Tzadok achala, she ate
one of the dried figs of רבי צדוק. Rabbi Tzadok. We're going
to see that Rabbi Tzadok basically was fasting and when he would
eat some food he would suck out the juice of the dried
fig. So Rashi says, but you know he was so like ill
and sickly that some of his,
you know, some of his germs, Rashi doesn't say germs, Rashi says
some of the sickness attached to the figs that he threw out.
So she found one of these thrown out figs ואינתיסא ומתה, ve'itnissa
umeta, and she became endangered and she died. רבי צדוק, Rabbi Tzadok,
because
Rabbi Tzadok יתיב ארבעין שנין בתעניתא. yativ arba'in shanin betanita. He was
for forty years in a fast, presumably not a continuous, it
would presumably like maybe it would be like, you know, he'd break
it in the, you know, every few days or in the evenings,
דלא ליחרב ירושלים, dela licherav Yerushalayim, that Yerushalayim should not be destroyed.
כי הוה אכיל מידי, Ki hava achil midi, when he would finally
like, you know, finally eat something... in between the fasts, הוה מתחזי
מאבראי, hava mitchazi me'ivrai, he would be so thin that you could
see the food going down from the outside. And כי הוה בריא
מעליא ki hava barya ma'alya he was a little bit healthier, מייתו
ליה גרוגרות, maysilei grogross, and he would they would bring him some
dried fig, מייץ מייהו maitz meyayuhu
he would suck out the water the juices, ושדי להו v'shadileihu and
he would throw it out. Okay so anyway so that's how she
died. Now כי הוה נח נפשא ki hava nach nafsha so obviously
that's in contrast to this very delicate woman, here he is he's
fasting himself. Also, you know, it's צדוק, Tzaddok, right? He's the צדיק,
tzaddik, he's the one person that is the one who's aware of
what's happening and through, you know, sort of like a very private
righteousness, right? It's also like, you know, he's obviously very righteousness, but
it's not having an impact on anybody else. Anyway, now
כי הוה נח נפשא ki hava nach nafsha when she died, אפיקתא
לכל דהבא וכספא ושדיתא בשוקא. afikta lechol dahava vechaspa veshadisa beshuka. So
apparently she was in the process of dying, she hadn't died yet,
and she took out all of her gold and silver and threw
it out into the marketplace. אמרה Amra and she said, האי למאי
מיבעיא לי? hai lemai mibaya li? What do I need this for
anymore? Right? It's now worthless. והיינו דכתיב, vehainu dicheshiv, that's what the
verse, כספם בחוצות ישליכו, kaspam bachutzot yashlichu, their silver they shall throw
out into the into the street. Okay so that's the end of
that story. Now אבא סקרא, Abba Sakra, now we spoke about the
סיקרא, Sikara, right? And סקרא Sakra is the Sicarii, which are the,
what's that Greek word that means like a dagger or something?
Latin for dagger.
Latin for dagger. So that was another name for the Zealots, right?
Okay, so אבא סיקרא, Abba Sikara, he was ריש בריוני דירושלים. reish
biryonei diyerushalayim. He was the head of the Zealots of Jerusalem. בר
אחתיה דרבן יוחנן בן זכאי, bar achtei d'rabban yochanan ben zakkai, but
is Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai's nephew. הוה שלח ליה, hava shelach leih,
now Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai sent for him, תא בצינעא לגבאי, ta
betzina legabai, come in private, meet with me. אתא, Ata, he came.
אמר ליה, Amar leih, so Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai said to him,
עד מתי עבדיתו הכי וקטליתו להו לעלמא דכפנא? ad matai avdisu hachi
vekatlisu lehu l'alma dechafna? How long are you going to stay in
your, sort of, you know, in the in your rebellion here? And
you're going to kill us a whole everybody through famine. אמר ליה,
Amar leih, so this אבא סקרא Abba Sakra said to him, מאי
אבידי? mai avidei? What can I do? דאמינא להו מידי, de'amina lehu
midi, if I tell them to do something else, קטלו לי, katlu
li, they'll kill me even though I'm the head, but you know,
they they won't listen to me. אמר ליה, Amar leih, חזי לי
תקנתא לדידי. chazi li takanta dididi. Look, let's try to figure out
some solution for me, דאיפוק, de'ipuk, that to get me out of
the city, אפשר דהוי הצלה פורתא. efshar dehavi hatzala purta. Maybe I
will be there'll be some small salvation, there'll be something that I'll
be able to, you know, maybe we'll be able to, you know,
do something. אמר ליה, Amar leih, נכות נפשך, nechot nafshach, so he
said fine, here's what we're going to do. בקיצירי, bekatziri, you know,
make it look like you're sick. ולייתו כולי עלמא לישאלו בך, veleisay
kulei alma lishaylu bach, let all of your students come, let everybody
come to ask after your welfare, you know, lie in bed for
many days, make it look like you're dying, everybody will come and
visit you, like put up a good show. ואייתי מידי סריא, ve'aiti
midi sarya, get something that is stinking, that's spoiled, ואגני גבך, ve'agnei
gabach, and let it put it in the bed next to you,
lie it next to you, ולימרו velayimru and people say, let and
let it be said, דנח נפשך, denach nafshach, that you died, and
then people will smell this thing, this rotting flesh. Okay so וליעלו
בך תלמידך, veleiailu bach talmideich, let your students go into your bedroom,
ולא ליעול בך איניש אחרינא, velau la bach inish achrini, nobody else,
cause you know, your students will be in on it, but you
don't want anybody else to know about what's going on, דלא לירגשון
בך, delo liyergeshun bach, then they cause if other people were there
they would sense that you're not dead, why? דקליל את, dekalil at,
because
you're lighter, דאינהו ידעי, de'innu yadei, that they know, דחיא קליל ממיטא,
dechai kalil mimita, that a live person is lighter than a dead
person. It's true, right? Because it's the way
you sort of balance your body when you're being lifted up or
something. Really? Was that?
You don't really, רש״י Rashi asks Joel Steiner about that.
No, but it is true, dead weight is heavier, but I think
I think that has something to do with the way you naturally
adjust balance your body to begin with. What?
He was pretty heavy.
That's true, he was pretty heavy. עבד הכי, Avda hachi, so they
did this. נכנס בו רבי אליעזר מצד אחד ורבי יהושע מצד אחר,
nichnas bo rabbi eliezer mitsad echad v'rabbi yehoshua mitsad acher, so Rabbi
Eliezer and Rabbi Yehoshua, who were the two future Rabbis of of
Rabbi Akiva, anyway, so they were his two students, they came, and
they took were taking him out in this coffin to out of
Jerusalem, because you can't bury a body in Jerusalem, so apparently they
would let people leave the city to bury people, that's also surprising.
כי מטו לפיתחא, ki matu lepitcha, when they came to the door,
בעו למדקיה, ba'u lemideikei, so the the Zealots who are guarding the
gates wanted to pierce him through to see if he was really
dead. אמר להו, Amar lehu, so he said to them, רש״י Rashi
says he means this אבא סיקרא Abba Sikara said to them, יאמרו
רבנן דקרו? yomru rabanan dakru? You want the Romans to say that
we actually, like, pierced our Rabbis? Like, you know, that'll be a
disgrace if they find out about that. בעו למדחפיה, ba'u lemitchafei, fine,
let's just push him around, see see if he moves. אמר להו,
Amar lehu, יאמרו רבנן דחפו? yomru rabanan dachfu? You want people to
say that we're so cruel that we are pushing around our the
Rabbis even in their death? Okay, so they didn't do anything to
him. פתחו ליה, Pitchu lei, they opened the door. פתחו ליה בבא,
Pitchu lei bava, they opened up the gate. נפיק, Nafik, he came
he was he went out. כי מטא להתם, Ki mata lehasam, now
when he managed to come to the camp of the Vespasian,
אמר, amar, he greeted Vespasian, he Cast off his disguise. He greeted
Vespasian and he said שלמא עלך מלכא *Shlama aleichah malka*, שלמא עלך
מלכא *Shlama aleichah malka*, peace to you king, peace to you king.
אמר ליה amar leih *Amar lei*, מחייבת תרי קטלא *Mechayeivat trei katla*,
so Vespasian said you are deserving of two deaths. חדא דלאו מלכא
אנא *Chada delav malka ana*, number one, I am not king, so
you are mocking me, וקקרית לי מלכא *vekakaryat li malka*, and you
are calling me king. ואי מלכא אנא *Veei malka ana*, if I
really am king, עד האידנא אמאי לא אתית לגבאי *ad idna amai
lo aseit legabai*, why didn't you come to me to earlier to
show your respect? אמר amar. ליה דקאמרת *Amar lei dekamart*, he said
back that you said לאו מלכא אנא *lav malka ana*, I am
not a king. איברא מלכא את *Ivra malka at*, in truth you
are king. דאי לאו מלכא את *De ee lav malka at*, if
you were not king,
Jerusalem would not be given over in your hands. דכתיב והלבנון באדיר
יפול *Dechtiv vehalevanon beadier yipol*, and the לבנון *Levanon* will fall in
the hands of the אדיר *adier*, the mighty. ואין אדיר אלא מלך
*Veein adier ela melech*, and אדיר *adier* means a king, דכתיב והיה
אדירו ממנו *dechtiv vehaya adiero mimenu*, the אדיר *adier* will be from
him, and the end of the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* is—Rashi quotes the
end of the פסוק *pasuk*, where is it? ומשלו מקרבו יצא *Umeshlo
mikirbo yeitzei*, and the ruler will come out from the midst, so
אדיר *adier* means king. ואין לבנון אלא בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash, *Veein
Levanon ela Beis Hamikdash*, and the לבנון *Levanon* is the בית המקדש
Beis HaMikdash *Beis Hamikdash*, שנאמר shenemar ההר הטוב הזה והלבנון *sheneemar hahar
hatov hazeh vehalevanon*, this mountain which is הר הבית *Har Habayis* and
לבנון *Levanon*. ודקאמרת *Vedekamart*, and that number one is I know you're
going to be king. ודקאמרת אי מלכא אנא *Vedekamart ei malka ana*,
if I were king, אמאי לא אתית לגבאי *amai lo aseisa legabai*,
why didn't I come to you עד האידנא *ad idna* till now?
בריוני דאית בהן לא שבקין *Biryonei deis behan lo shavkin*, because of
the zealots. אמר ליה *Amar lei*, אילו חבית של דבש ודרקון כרוך
עליה *ilu chavis shel devash vedarkon karuch aleha*, if you had a
barrel of honey and a דרקון *darkon*, a dragon was sort of
wrapped around it, a serpent was wrapped around it. לא היו שוברין
את החבית בשביל הדרקון *Lo hayu shovrin es hachavis bishvil hadarkon*? Wouldn't
you break the barrel in order to get rid of the serpent?
So here too, what you should have done is you should have
broken the walls of Jerusalem and, you know,
and that would have gotten rid—we would have come in and you
would have dealt and, you know, that would have just ended the
whole thing earlier, would have gotten rid of the zealots, so you
had a solution. אישתיק ishtik *Ishtik*,
he didn't have a response. קרי ליה רב יוסף Rav Yosef ואיכא
דאמרי רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva *Kari lei Rav Yosef veika deamri Rabbi
Akiva*, רב יוסף *Rav Yosef* and some say רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
*Rabbi Akiva* said about this that יוחנן בן זכאי *Yochanan ben Zakkai*
was—wasn't able to find a response. משיב חכמים אחור ודעתם יסכל meshiv
chachamim achor ve-da'atam yesakel. *Meishiv chachamim achor vedaatam yesakel*, that God sometimes
causes the wise ones to, you know, retreat backwards and their wisdom
to be foolish. Okay, he lost his ability, he should have known
better, he knew how to respond better, he should have responded better.
איבעי ליה למימר *Ibaei lei lemeimar*, what he should have said was
ליה *lei*, שקלינן צבתא ושקלינן ליה לדרקון *shaklinan tzavta veshaklinan lei ledarkon*,
no, if there was a serpent around a barrel of honey, we
wouldn't just destroy the barrel of honey. First we would try to
get rid of the serpent without destroying the barrel. שקלינן צבתא *Shaklinan
tzavta*, we would take tongs, ושקלינן ליה לדרקון *veshaklinan lei ledarkon*, we
would remove the serpent, וקטלינן ליה *vekatlinan lei*, and we would kill
it, וחביתא שבקינן לה *vachavita shavkinan lah*, we'd save the barrel of
honey. So here too, we thought we could find a way to
deal with the
zealots without having to destroy Jerusalem. So that's not an answer. Okay.
Anyway, אדהכי *Adeihachi*, but basically Vespasian was saying, you know, you should
have—you should have dealt with the situation if you and not waited
this long. אדהכי *Adeihachi*, while they were having this conversation, אתי פריסתקא
*asei pristaka* עליה *aleh*, some messenger came מרומי *miRomi* from Rome, אמר
ליה *amar lei* and said קום *kum*, get up, דמית ליה קיסר
*demeis lei keisar*, the Caesar has died, ואמרי הנהו חשיבי דרומי *veamri
hanu chashivei deRomi*, and the important ones, presumably like the senate in
Rome, have decided לאושיבך ברישא *leoshivach bereisha*, to make you the Caesar.
הוה סיים חד מסאני *Havah sayeim chad masanei*, now Vespasian was wearing
one shoe, בעא למיסיימיה לאחרינא *beia lemisyameia leachrina*, he wanted to put
on the other shoe, לא עייל ביה *lo ayeil beih*, he couldn't,
למישלפא לאידך *lemishlafa leidach*,
so he tried to take off the one that he had on,
לא נפק *lo nafak*, and he couldn't get the one on off
and he couldn't get the one off on.
אמר מאי האי *Amar mai hai*, what's going on? אמר ליה *Amar
lei*, לא תצטער *lo tztateir*, don't worry that this is happening,
שמועה טובה אתיא
לך *shemuah tovah asya lach*, you heard a good
report, דכתיב שמועה טובה תדשן עצם
*dechtiv shemuah tovah tedashen atzem*,
that a good report causes your bones to be fattened. So therefore
your feet swell with a sense of pride and gladness and you
can't get one shoe off and you can't get the other one
on. אלא מאי תקנתיה *Ela mai takanteih*, so what can you do
now? Because he's got to get a shoe—his shoes off. ליתי איניש
דלא מיתבא דעתך מיניה *Leisi inish dela misava daatach mineih*,
go bring somebody who you—who you know, who's disturbing to you, who
you don't appreciate, you know, you don't like being in their presence,
וחליף קמך *vechalif kamach*, and let him walk in front of you,
דכתיב ורוח נכאה תיבש גרם *dechtiv veruach necheiah tyavesh garem*, and a
downtrodden spirit will—will, you know, dry up the bones. Okay, so it'll
restore your feet to—to their right proportions. עבד הכי *Avad hachi*, he
did that and it worked, he got his shoe off. Okay, anyway,
אמר ליה ומאחר דחכמיתו כולי האי *amar lei umiaechar dechachmitu kulei hai*,
since you're so wise, עד האידנא אמאי לא אתיתו לגבאי *ad idna
amai lo aseitu legabai*, why didn't you come to me? You could
have found another way. You said you didn't want to destroy Jerusalem,
but you could have found some way, like you did, some scheme
if you're so smart. אמר ליה ולאו אמרי לך *Amar lei velav
amri lach*, I told you... I told you why I didn't come
to you because we had these Zealots. ולא אמרי לך אמר ליה
אנא נמי אמרי לך? Didn't I tell you you should have had
a way to deal with them? Okay, so they're going around in
circles. Anyway, okay, אמר ליה מיזל אזילנא. Amar lei meizal azilna. So
now, fine, Vespasian says look, I got to go back to Rome,
ואינש אחרינא משדרנא, ve-inash achrina meshadrana, and I'm going to send somebody
else because we're still taking over, we're still conquering ירושלים, Yerushalayim, I'm
going to send some other, some general. אלא בעי מינאי מידי דאתן
לך. Ela bei minai midi de-aten lach. Ask of me something that
I can give you. אמר ליה תן לי יבנה וחכמיה. Amar lei
ten li Yavne ve-chachameiha. Give me Yavne and its wise men, the
very famous statement which is, you know, רבן יוחנן בן זכאי, Rabban
Yochanan ben Zakkai, you know, it's interesting because this is introduced right
to חכימו כולי האי, chakimu kulei hai, that you know, you're so
wise. And רבן יוחנן בן זכאי Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai is trying
to figure out a way to like preserve something. Right, we didn't
want to destroy ירושלים, Yerushalayim, we're trying to find a way to
preserve it and so on. And so what he realizes and also
echoes back right to when רבן יוחנן בן זכאי Rabban Yochanan ben
Zakkai says find a way to get me out of the city,
maybe I will have הצלה פורתא. hatzalah porta. What was the phrase
back there? It was הצלה פורתא hatzalah porta or some... yeah. So
like a little thing to preserve. So recognizing we're not going to
be able to save the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash but there is
something but what we have to do is figure out how to
move beyond it, how to go to the next stage. And of
course, this is the whole transition from a temple-centered ירושלים, Yerushalayim, you
know, Judaism to a rabbinic-centered one. Fine, the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash,
is destroyed, we have to come to terms with that, that's going
to happen. You know, let's move on to think what's the next
sort of focal point is going to be, you know, what's going
to bring us into the future is the focus on Torah, תן
לי יבנה וחכמיה. ten li Yavne ve-chachameiha. So that's what he asks
for. What's by the way never explained by these stories is like
why was he offering him something? It was like oh, I'm so
impressed with how wise you are because you were the one to
first tell me that I was going to be the Caesar. Like
what did he do that he was deserving of some type of
a, of like an accommodation. Anyway, fine, so give me anyway...
there's a phrase of something here. You know, אבא סיקרא Abba Sikra
is a phrase of his fall. Right. And his followers are apparently
afraid of the rabbis or the population, which is why they won't...
aha, raise רבי יוחנן's Rabbi Yochanan body. Aha. Maybe he's also afraid
of something. I mean, he's going to conquer this country but they're
going to, you know, he has the religious implication...
oh, you have to rule over it, that's interesting. So you might
as well... oh that's an interesting point. Oh that's an interesting point.
Maybe he realizes that רבן יוחנן בן זכאי Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai
is in a leadership position and he's doing it for more political
issues. That's a good point, yeah.
But there's also another tradition that a new ruler would start his
rule by making gestures of compassion.
Oh, I see, very... ah, that's nice. Prisoners... oh, that's nice, okay,
that's nice. Got it, got it. Okay, so תן לי יבנה וחכמיה,
ten li Yavne ve-chachameiha, ושלשולתא דרבי גמליאל, ve-shishulta de-Rabbi Gamliel, and the
sort of the chain of רבי גמליאל, Rabbi Gamliel, meaning the family
of רבי גמליאל Rabbi Gamliel of the נשיא. Nasi.
So he wants to preserve like the religious, you know, a religious
center, the Torah and so on, which is going to be the
religious future, and he wants to preserve like political leadership and the
נשיא Nasi and, you know, the status that comes with the house
of the נשיא. Nasi. ואסוותא דמסיין ליה לרבי צדוק. ve-asvata de-masyan lei
le-Rabbi Tzadok.
And very interesting, and then the other one was a very much
less of a national one and much of a personal one. Give
me some type of a, you know, doctors that will take care
and heal רבי צדוק. Rabbi Tzadok. Because you know, so
it's a little funny I mean trying to sort of figure out
how that fits into the other two, but some sense like not
only looking at the larger national picture but focusing at, you know,
the individual acts of righteousness that have to be recognized. So even
רבי צדוק... Rabbi Tzadok...
there's a lot of things, a lot of details that are mirrored
among these stories, like the shoe, you know, with the...
right. Oh, I wasn't thinking about that. She wasn't wearing shoes.
Right, and then the nephew of the Caesar and this guy.
Oh,
that's a very good point. So it's just a way of essentially
tying it, weaving back the previous story. But that's a good point,
the shoe also, yeah.
You know that צדיק tzaddik was fasting so that the temple wouldn't
be destroyed. Right.
And now the temple's going to be destroyed. Accepted
by Rabbi... oh, I see.
Saying, you know, even if it's destroyed, it's gotta have a healing.
Oh, that's nice, oh that's very nice. You mean sort of like
the same idea temple's going to be destroyed, we have to move
on, so we're going to move to יבנה Yavne and transition that
way. רבי צדוק Rabbi Tzadok was fasting it wouldn't be destroyed, now
we're going to have to find a way to transition to the
next stage. Right.
And he's going in the direction of life.
Right, right, that's a very, that's a very beautiful point. I really
like that. Okay. קרי עליה רב יוסף ואיתימא רבי עקיבא. Kara aleih
Rav Yosef ve-iteima Rabbi Akiva. And now רב יוסף and רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva
responded and they said, משיב חכמים אחור ודעתם יסכל. They did not
like this response. That was a foolish response. איבעי ליה למימר ליה
שבקינהו הדא זימנא. Ibei lei le-meimar lei shavkinehu hada zimna. He should
have said to him, you want, you want a request? The request
is leave us! Don't destroy us! והוא סבר, ve-hu savar, but רבן
יוחנן בן זכאי Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai was of opinion דלמא כולי
האי לא עביד, dilma kulei hai lo avid, maybe that much he
won't do. And here's the phrase again: והצלה פורתא נמי לא הוי.
ve-hatzalah porta nami lo havei.
And then I won't even get this little salvation. And of course,
this is so appropriate for רבי עקיבא because רבי עקיבא of course
was, you know... backed Bar Kochba and he was very messianic and
wanted the restoration of Jewish sovereignty and so on, right? So Rabbi
Akiva did not want to come to terms with the new reality.
He wanted to hold on to the old reality of the בית
המקדש Beit HaMikdash. and of Jewish sovereignty and so on, whereas he
was accepting, you know, that יבנה Yavne replaces בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash
you can have the נשיא's Nasi house without having the same type
of sovereignty that we had before, right? But that was not Rabbi
Akiva.
Okay. לא הוי. lo havei. אסוותא דמסין ליה לרבי צדוק מאי היא?
asvatta demassin lei le-Rabbi Tzadok mai hi? What was this healing for
the healing of Rabbi Tzadok? Or the doctors? יומא קמא אשקיוה מיא
דפארי. yoma kama ashkyuha maya defari. The first day when they tried
to, you know, sort of get him back to health, they made
him drink water that had like bran had been soaked in it.
So it had like a little bit of nutrition, but it was
still very, you know, mostly water. He was able to absorb it
in his body. למחר מיא דסיפוקא. lemachar maya desipuka.
The next day water that had Rashi says like a certain type
of, some type of a wheat that was,
you know, what does Rashi say? Maya de-par... bran. Yeah, the מיא
דפארי maya depari I thought was bran.
Yeah, he said they're both,
and this מיא דסיפוקא maya desipuka Rashi says, yeah, no, Rashi says
with a little bit of flour, bran with a little bit of
flour.
Okay. למחר מיא דקמחא, lemachar maya de-kimcha, the third day water that
had that had flour soaked in it. Okay, so each day it
was more it was a liquid diet with more and more nutrients
עד דרווח מעיה פורתא פורתא ad deravach me'eih purta purta until his
stomach expanded little by little. Okay, I really like your explanation, David,
that it's like basically it's sort of in a very personal way
symbolizing the getting over the חורבן הבית Churban HaBayit and transitioning into
a new type of a state.
And the word פורתא purta appears a lot in this. What? The
word פורתא purta appears a lot in the same word that he
used for הצלה פורתא, hatzalah purta, a little salvation.
Oh,
very nice point, very nice. Okay. אזדו שדרו לטיטוס. azdu shadru le-Titus.
So then Vespasian sent Titus. ואמר אי אלוהימו צור חסיו בו. ve-amar
ei eloheimo tzur chasayu vo.
So where is their God, the rock that they have found refuge
in? So, so that's a פסוק from דברים, Devarim, you know, he
will say, where actually the little circle should have been before the
אמר. Anyway, he will say, where is their God? זה טיטוס הרשע,
ze Titus HaRasha, this verse refers to the wicked Titus, שחירף וגידף
כלפי מעלה, she-chiref ve-gidef klapei ma'alah, that he blasphemed towards God. מה
עשה? ma asah? What did he do? By the way, you'll notice
that Jerusalem isn't being given over in the hand of a Caesar,
it's being given over in the hand of Titus. And before he
said it was going to be given over as Vespasian. Tosafot says,
well no, since it was an extension of the siege
that
Vespasian laid, it was like it was being given over in the
hand of the Caesar. And Titus would later become Caesar. Very good.
Okay, so מה עשה, ma asah, what did he do? תפס זונה
בידו, tafas zonah beyado, he took a prostitute in his hand, ונכנס
לבית קדשי קדשים, ve-nichnas le-veit kodshei kodashim, he went into the Holy
of Holies. Notice by the way we have completely now jumped over
the entire, you know, burning and destroying of Jerusalem, the breaching of
the walls, we're now like all the way to, you know, entering
into the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash He went into the Holy of
Holies, והציע ספר תורה, ve-hetzia sefer torah, he spread out a sefer
torah, which I don't know if there was supposed to have been
in the Holy of Holies, ועבר עליה עבירה, ve-avar alei aveirah, and
he basically had sex with his prostitute on a sefer torah in
the Holy of Holies. ונטל סייף, ve-natal sayif, he took a sword,
וגידר את הפרוכת, ve-gider et ha-parochet, and he pierced the parochet, the
veil between the Holy of Holies and the היכל. heichal. ונעשה נס,
ve-na'asah nes,
and a miracle happened, not a saving miracle, והיה דם מבצבץ ויוצא,
ve-hayah dam mivatzbetz ve-yotzei, and there was blood spurting out of the
curtain of the Holy of Holies. Right, Tosafot says that it was
done to show how difficult the destruction of the בית המקדש Beit
HaMikdash was, but it also could have been done to mislead Titus.
So כסבור, kasavar, and Titus thought, הרג את עצמו. harag et atzmo.
So there's a euphemism here, he killed himself, but it means he
thought he had murdered God. שנאמר שאגו צורריך בקרב מועדך שמו אותותם
אותות. shene'emar sha'agu tzorecha bekerev mo'adecha samu ototam otot. Your
enemies have cried out in the midst of your meeting places, meaning
the בית המקדש where you God cause your presence to be, you
know, to dwell,
they have made their signs into signs. They have seen this as
a sign that they have killed you, that they... אבא חנן אומר
מי כמוך חסין יה. Abba Chanan omer mi kamocha chasin yah.
Who is like you, who with the strength of God? מי כמוך
חסין וקשה. mi kamocha chasin ve-kasheh.
Who is like you God that you are so, you know, restraining
and hard, שאתה שומע ניאוצו וגידופו של אותו רשע ושותק. she-attah shome'a
ni'utzo ve-giduffo shel oto rasha ve-shotek. You can hear the cursing and
the blaspheming of that wicked person and be silent. So right, you
know, it's a little way the rabbis are like both sort of
praising and astounded that God could allow such a thing to occur.
So the way of expressing their like, you know, their like
incomprehensibility to understand how could this happen, not only the בית המקדש
be destroyed, but God's name be so desecrated and there be no
response from heaven, so they reframe reframe it as a way of
praising God, okay? So דבי רבי ישמעאל תנא devei Rabbi Yishmael tana
מי כמכה באילים ה׳ mi kamocha ba'eilim Hashem
who is like You amongst the mighty gods, מי כמכה באלמים mi
kamocha ba'ilmim who is like You amongst those who are silent? מה
ma that you're able to be so silent at this moment. מה
עשה ma asa what did then Titus do? נטל את הפרוכת natal
et haparochet he took the parochet ועשאו כמין גרגותני ve'asao kemin gargutni
he made it like a sack והביא כל כלים שבמקדש vehevi kol
keilim shebamikdash he brought all the vessels of the Mikdash והניח בהן
vehiniach bahen and put it in it והושיבן בספינה vehoshiban bisfina and
he put it on a boat לילך להשתבח בעירו lelech lehishtabach be'iro
to go and to praise himself in his city שנאמר as the
verse says ובכן ראיתי רשעים קבורים ubchen raiti reshaim kburim now
the simple sense of this verse does not refer to it but
we're going to reread it. I have seen wicked that are buried
ובאו ממקום קודש יהלכו ubau mimakom kodesh yehalchu and they have come
and from a holy place they have come וישתכחו בעיר אשר כן
עשו veyishtakchu ba'ir asher ken asu
and they have been forgotten in the city which they have made.
Now what does that mean? אל תקרי קבורים al tikrei kburim don't
say I have seen them buried אלא קבוצים ela kbutzim
I have seen them gathered, the wicked gathered. אל תקרי וישתכחו al
tikrei veyishtakchu they'll be forgotten אלא וישתבחו ela veyishtabchu
they will praise themselves in their cities. איכא דאמרי ika de'amri some
say קבורים ממש kburim mamash no, it does mean buried דאפילו מילי
דמיטמרן de'afilu mili demitamran even
the buried treasures איגלי להו iglei lehu was revealed to Titus and
his armies. Okay, אמר עלה נחש amar ala nachsho now there he
was crossing the Mediterranean to return to Rome and a
big wave rose up שבים לטובעו shabayam letovo in the sea to
drown him. אמר כמדומה אני amar kmidumeh ani it seems to me
שאלוהיהם של אלו she'eloheihem shel elu אין גבורתו אלא במים ein gvurato
ela bamayim oh sure here's where God wants to take me on
in the ocean with the water because their God only knows his
strength is only in water. בא פרעה ba Paroh when Pharaoh came
טבעו במים tavo bamayim he drowned him in the water ובא סיסרא
uba Sisra and when Sisera came טבעו במים tavo bamayim he drowned
him in the water of course you know that because one of
the פסוקים psukim there in שירת דבורה Shirat Devorah says נחל קישון
גרפם nachal Kishon grefam
and so
on. אף הוא עומד עלי לטובעני במים af hu omed alai letovani
bamayim
here too he wants to fight me in the water he couldn't
fight me back on land. אם גיבור הוא im gibor hu if
God is really mighty יעלה ליבשה ויעשה עמי מלחמה ya'ale layabasha veya'aseh
imi milchama let's fight on land okay let's see if he can
fight me on land. יצתה בת קול ואמרה yatzta bat kol ve'amra
a heavenly voice came out and said לו לרשע בן רשע בן
בנו של עשו הרשע lo larasha ben rasha ben bno shel Esav
harasha
wicked son of a wicked grandson of Esau the wicked there's also
the tie-in of Rome to Edom. בריה קלה יש לי בעולמי birya
kala yesh li be'olami I have
a tiny little creature in my world ויתוש שמה veyitush shma it's
known as a gnat ואמאי קרי לה בריה קלה ve'amai kari lei
birya kala why is it called a tiny little creature a light
one דמעלנא אית לה ומפקנא לית לה demalna it leih umafkana leit
leih that it takes in food and apparently it does not excrete
it I don't know why that means it's a light creature anyway.
עלה ליבשה ותעשה עמה מלחמה ala layabasha veta'aseh ima milchama
go on to the land and try to fight against this gnat.
עלה ליבשה ala layabasha so he landed בא יתוש ba yitush a
gnat came ונכנס בחוטמו venichnas bechotmo went up his nose ונקר במוחו
venakar bemocho and started piercing in his skull you know in his
brain and eating away there. שבע שנים sheva shanim for seven years
יומא חד הוה קא חליף בבבא דבי נפחא yoma chad hava ka
chalif bebaba devei napa and obviously this was causing him tremendous distress
one day he was walking by the doorway of a blacksmith. שמע
קול ארזפתא shama kol arzafta
so he heard the sound of like the beating of what is
it on the anvil like is that what it's called the anvil
whatever? אישתיק
and for the gnat was like startled by that harsh sound and
he stopped you know eating away at his brain. אמר איכא תקנתא
amar ika takanta ah there's a way to at least get a
little relief. כל יומא מייתו נפחא kol yoma maitu napa every day
they would bring a blacksmith ומחו קמיה umacho kamia and he would
bang
before
him. לנוכרי lenochri if he was a non-Jew יהיב ליה ארבע זוזי
yahiv leih arba zuzei he'd give him four zuz. לישראל leYisrael if
he was a Jew אמר ליה he said to him מסתייך דקחזית
בסנאך mistayach dekachazit besanach it's enough that you have seen your enemy
and you've seen me in anguish so that's enough payment for you.
עד תלתין יומין עבד הכי ad tlatzin yomin abad hachi for thirty
days they did this and it gave him some relief. מכאן ואילך
mikan ve'eilach after that כיון דדש דש keivan dedash dash once the
gnat sort of grew accustomed it was accustomed it developed a what-do-you-call-it
an immunity to it it's like the strain after you know you
give it some medicine it develops an immunity to the strain. תניא
tanya we done a Braitia אמר רבי פנחס בן ערובא amar Rabbi
Pinchas ben Aruvah
I was
amongst the
prestigious people of Rome וכשמת ukshemet and when Titus died פצעו את
מוחו patzu et mocho they cracked open his skull ומצאו בו umatzu
bo and they found in his skull that the gnat had grown
and the gnat had become כציפור דרור ketzippor dror like this wild
bird משקלו שני סלעים mishkalo shnei sela'im which weighs two sela'im. במתניתא
תנא bematnita tana in a Braitia it taught כגוזל בן שנה kgozal
ben shana like a pigeon a year old משקלו שני ליטרין mishkalo
shnei litrin that weighs two litrin. אמר אביי amar Abaye נקטינן naktinan
and
we have a tradition פיו של נחושת piv shel nechoshet it had
a mouth of brass וצפורניו של ברזל vetzipornav shel barzel
and its claws of iron. fingernails was of iron. Okay, so this
was eating away, I don't know how it developed brass and iron
in the middle of his head, but anyway, maybe a little bit
also echoing the
blacksmith theme. כי הוי כמיית Ki hava kamayis when he was dying,
אמר להו amar lehu he said to the people, לקלייה לההוא גברא
Liklyeh l'hahu gavra
burn my, you know, burn me, cremate me, ונבדרי לקיטמיה אשבעה ימי
U'nivdrei l'kitmei ashivah yamei and spread my ashes on the seven seas,
דלא לישכחיה אלהא דיהודאי וליוקמיה בדינא D'lo lishkachayeh eloha d'yehudai v'lyokmayeh b'dina
that the God of the Jews should not find me in death
and make me stand in judgment in the afterlife. So somehow he
believed that if his body had been scattered and the ashes scattered,
he would be saved from judgment in the afterlife. Okay, and we
will continue with the next sort of story that relates to this,
pick up with this tomorrow.
All right, that was fun.
Exactly. That's the only time people learn this גמרא. Gemara. But I
appreciated everybody's input. That was really a